Guide to the Bert Hansen Collection of Advertising Fans circa early 20th century-circa 2003 PR 438
New-York Historical Society
Bert Hansen collection of advertising fans
circa early 20th century-circa 2003
New-York Historical Society
Hansen, Bert, 1944-
PR 438
1.26 Linear feet in 3 document boxes
The collection holds 114 advertising fans collected by historian and gay activist Bert Hansen. Represented in the collection are funeral homes (many of which are owned by African-Americans), drugstores, drug products, coal supply, retail stores, churches, printing services, and others. The fans are mostly undated but seem to range from the first half of the 20th century to the early 2000s. Most fans include religious, scenic, photographic, or other imagery. The later fans include public service messages and advocacy, as well as advertising.
Arrangement
The collection is in the original order as presented to N-YHS by the collector, which generally was grouped by the estimated age of the fan (i.e., "antique," "vintage," "modern"). Each fan is designated with an item number (e.g., BH.001); these numbers were assigned by the collector.
Access Restrictions
For more information on making arrangements to consult the collection, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the collector, Bert Hansen, in November 2021.
Scope and Contents
The collection holds 114 advertising fans collected by historian and gay activist Bert Hansen. About 30 of the fans advertise funeral homes, many of which make clear their African-American ownership or connection to the Black community. About 30 fans advertise drugstores, drug products, or certain medical services, such as dental work and chiropractors. Other businesses represented are milling, coal supply, car dealers, retail stores (e.g., home furnishings, dry goods), churches, and others. Some fans seem to be samples that advertise the services of the fan's printer. Fans characterized by the collector as "modern," that is, dating from approximately the 1990s to the early 2000s, also include public service messages (e.g., railway crossing safety, environmental/clean water), advocacy (e.g., Gay Men's Health Crisis/AIDS), and Broadway theater publicity, among others.
Most of the fans include imagery, such as drawings or photographs. Images often depict scenes that are religious (usually Christian), serene country/rural, romantic/sentimental Americana, drawings of products, and others. Some are more text-heavy about products, especially those related to drugstores or later public service messages. Geographically, the bulk of the fans are from the United States, but no particular state or region predominates.
The bulk of the fans are undated. The terms "antique," "vintage," and "modern" are used in the container list. These were provided by the collector. It appears that "antique" refers to fans estimated to date from the first half of the 20th century, "vintage" refers to those estimated to date from the 1950s to 1970s, and "modern" to those estimated to date from the 1980s to early 2000s.
All fans in the collection are listed in the container list. The donor provided an Excel spreadsheet with the collection that includes the collector's detailed descriptions of the items and commentary on many of them. A copy of these descriptions is included in each of the three boxes holding the collection. The descriptions used in this finding aid's container list were derived from elements of the collector's Excel spreadsheet, along with the processing archivist's observations of the objects. The container list descriptions provide a basic physical description of the fan (as provided by the collector) and imagery, reference to the product or business/organization advertised, and, if indicated on the fan, the printer/manufacturer. The few dates in the container list are those explicitly recorded on the fan or those that could be readily determined from context.
Biographical / Historical
Bert Hansen (1944-) is Professor Emeritus of History at Baruch College of the City University of New York, where he taught from 1991-2015. His principal areas of research and writing have been in science, medicine and public health. Since the 1970s, Hansen has been an activist for gay rights and, in the 1980s, engaged with the AIDS movement. During the course of his professional research and activism, he has collected a range of documents, scientific instruments, prints, objects, and other material that he has donated to various institutions, including Yale, the New York Academy of Medicine, and others, including New-York Historical Society.
(The above note was derived from Bert Hansen's website. A fuller note and links to his writings, etc. can be found there: https://www.berthansen.com/ )
Related Materials
N-YHS's Ephemera Collection (PR 264) holds about 500 advertising postcards that were also collected and, in 2000, donated by Bert Hansen.
Advertising fans.; Advertising -- United States.; Drugstores -- United States.; Funeral homes -- United States.
- Inventory and item notes provided by collector Bert Hansen, 2021 (Box 1)
- BH-001. Antique with wooden handle (Box 1, Folder BH.001)
  Scope and Contents
  Wide oval. Portrait of George Washington. Coopersburg Casket Company, Coopersburg, Pennsylvania.
- BH-002. Antique with continuous cardboard handle (Box 1, Folder BH.002)
  Dye cut rectangular with image partly protruding. Shamrock brand of Sunkist Valencias (oranges), from Northern Orange County. Printer: Western Litho. Co., in Los Angeles.
- BH-003. Antique with continuous cardboard handle (Box 1, Folder BH.003)
  Balloon shape. Illustration on front of woman holding a product (Triena brand) with images of other packages, for Allied Drug Products Co., Chattanooga, Tennessee; and illustration on back of Dr. Thacher's laxative compound of senna and rhubarb. R. L. Hopper, General Merchandise, Elwood, Texas.
- BH-004. Antique with continuous cardboard handle (Box 1, Folder BH.004)
  Rounded rectangle. Color painting of girl, boy, and dog outside a drug store, with publicity for brands Nature's Remedy laxative and Tums. Hepler's Drug Store, New Bethlehem, Pennsylvania.
- BH-005. Antique with continuous cardboard handle (Box 1, Folder BH.005)
  Rounded rectangle. Color painting on front of a sailboat moving fast; blank on back. Publicity for brands Nature's Remedy laxative and Tums.
- BH-006. Antique with continuous cardboard handle (Box 1, Folder BH.006)
  Rounded rectangle. Front has exactly the same text and image as BH-005 (color painting of a sailboat moving fast), but has content on back. Publicity for brands Nature's Remedy laxative and Tums. The Dickinson Drug Co., Abingdon, Illinois.
- BH-007. Antique with continuous cardboard handle (Box 1, Folder BH.007)
  Rounded rectangle. Color painting ("First Aid" by Norman Price) of 3 children, with a dog, play-acting pharmacist, nurse and patient. Ernest F. Birbeck, Optician, Plaza Hotel, Camden, N.J.
- BH-008. Antique with continuous cardboard handle (Box 1, Folder BH.008)
  Rounded badge shape. Color painted illustration of an autumn harvest scene with corn shocks in autumn light. Boydton Drug Store, Inc. Boydton, Virginia. Printer: Merchants Pub. Co., Kalamazoo, Michigan.
- BH-009. Antique with continuous cardboard handle (Box 1, Folder BH.009)
  Rounded badge shape. Color painted illustration portrait of young woman in swimsuit. The Selma Drug Co., Selma, North Carolina. Printer: The Harrison Co., Inc. Union City, Indiana.
- BH-010. Antique with continuous cardboard handle (Box 1, Folder BH.010)
  Circular. Color painted illustration of woman in bathing suit waving to someone from her seat on a sailboat out on the water. Lebanon Fair. Printer: Boyer Printing & Binding Co., Lebanon, Pennsylvania.
- BH-011. Antique with continuous cardboard handle (Box 1, Folder BH.011)
  Color illustration of Diana or Artemis, the hunter with bow, arrows, and a sleek greyhound like dog. Publicity for brand 666 product line (liquid, salve, tablet, nose drops). Stover's, Trenton [New Jersey?].
- BH-012. Antique with continuous cardboard handle (Box 1, Folder BH.012)
  Squarish badge shape. Color painting of little girl holding a puppy beside a pond. Dr. Wm. H. Stippich, chiropractor and natureopath, Meriden, Conn.
- BH-013. Antique with continuous cardboard handle (Box 1, Folder BH.013)
  Pentagonal shape. Color painted illustration of little boy pushing a wheelbarrow holding 7 babies. Publicity for Dicks' Chillifuge, a malaria remedy. F. A. Dicks and Co., Inc., New Orleans.
- BH-014. Antique tri-fold expandable around a metal grommet (Box 1, Folder BH.014)
  Vase shape when closed. Color painting of Jesus on the Mount of Olives. Swallow Funeral Home, Northampton, Pennsylvania. Printer: Messenger Corp., Auburn, Indiana.
- BH-015. Antique tri-fold expandable around a metal grommet (Box 1, Folder BH.015)
  Vase shape when closed. Color painting of an American flag on a pole flying in the wind, against a dramatic set of clouds, with Pledge of Allegiance. One section on the back has photo of the proprietor and listing for Echternacht Funeral Home, at 1900 Central Ave., [Kansas City, Kansas]. Added to central piece by hand: "Stephens Memorial Meth. Church."
- BH-016. Antique tri-fold expandable around a metal grommet (Box 1, Folder BH.016)
  Vase shape when closed. Color photograph of a formal flower arrangement with a black background. This seems to be a printer's sample; Printer: U.O. Colson Company, Paris, Illinois. Stamped "For Minnows, Worms, and Accessories, call AT 5908 Troost."
- BH-017. Antique tri-fold expandable around a metal grommet (Box 1, Folder BH.017)
  Vase shape when closed. Color photograph of a formal flower arrangement (mostly red roses) with a blank green background. Lawrence D. Rouse Inc. with addresses in St. Albans and Wantaugh on Long Island, NY. Printer: Messenger Corp., Auburn, Indiana.
- BH-018. Antique tri-fold expandable around a metal grommet. (Box 1, Folder BH.018)
  Vase shape when closed. Color photograph of white church in between two forested hills. F.L. Wadhams & Sons, Inc., (coal, fuel oil, grain and feed), Torrington, Connecticut. Printer: Newton Mfg. Co., Newton, Iowa.
- BH-019. Antique tri-fold expandable around a metal grommet, circa 1946 (Box 1, Folder BH.019)
  Vase shape when closed. Color painting of rural scene centered on farmhouse with smoke rising from the chimney in autumn. Main text on back appears to be from a women's apparel shop, Hartley's, in Miami, but that might be fiction as it is clearly a printer's sample since it has prices for fans in bulk. Printer: U.O. Colson Co.
- BH-020. Antique tri-fold expandable around a metal grommet (Box 1, Folder BH.020)
  Vase shape when closed. Color painting of a winter scene among tall trees with a country house in the center, with lighted windows and smoke rising from the chimney. Woodruff Coal Co., Bridgeton, New Jersey. Printer: Banker's Advertising Co., Iowa City, Iowa. (Copy 1, identical to BH-021)
- BH-021. Antique tri-fold expandable around a metal grommet (Box 1, Folder BH.021)
  Vase shape when closed. Color painting of a winter scene among tall trees with a country house in the center, with lighted windows and smoke rising from the chimney. Woodruff Coal Co., Bridgeton, New Jersey. Printer: Banker's Advertising Co., Iowa City, Iowa. (Copy 2, identical to BH-020)
- BH-022. Antique tri-fold expandable around a metal grommet (Box 1, Folder BH.022)
  Vase shape when closed. Sentimental painting of "A Faithful Guardian," scene of a raft bearing a sitting but alert St. Bernard dog and a small boy seated between his paws and holding on to the dog's furry chest, looking frightened. Field's Stationery, West Somerville, Massachusetts. Printer: Leroy, Inc., Union City, N.J.
- BH-023. Antique tri-fold expandable around a metal grommet (Box 1, Folder BH.023)
  Vase shape when closed. Color photograph, wide angle of a garden park in the south on a body of water, with four women in colorful ball gowns promenading on a walk and across a footbridge. J.W. Hallowell & Sons, Inc., (Chevrolet, Oldsmobile), Federalsburg, Maryland.
- BH-024. Antique tri-fold expandable around a metal grommet (Box 1, Folder BH.024)
  Vase shape when closed. Painted illustration of southern scenes: a bayou with a riverboat under a moonlit sky, young elite couple, log cabin with a smoking chimney, and two Black men playing banjoes seated on the dock. Kreamer Funeral Service, Annville, Pennsylvania.
- BH-025. Antique quadri-fold around a metal grommet (Box 1, Folder BH.025)
  Fan-shaped when closed. This style is uncommon and is the only one in this collection. Drawings of two birds in a tree. Lincoln-Income Life Insurance Co., Louisville, Kentucky.
- BH-026. Antique single piece with wood handle, only foreign example (Box 1, Folder BH.026)
  Shaped like a feathered fan. From Spain, the only non-American fan in the collection. Painted to look like a feathered fan, including a black-and-white portrait photograph of the actress Marion Davies. Publicity for remedy Digestona Chorro from Gabriel Ruiz Chorro, in the town of Elche in Spain. Printer: Union Bolsera Madrilena. Text is in Spanish.
- BH-027. Antique with wooden handle (Box 1, Folder BH.027)
  Flat-top oval. Color painting of "Capri and Vesuvius." Heater's Barber Shop (and hunting and fishing supplies), Alburtis, Pennsylvania.
- BH-028. Antique with wooden handle (Box 1, Folder BH.028)
  Rounded rectangle. 1st of 8 fans with the same kind of black and white photograph in a light green architectural border. This fan's photograph is titled "A Shady Spot" and noted as copyright 1902 by Chas. Williams. The product being promoted is "laxative celeri bromure" for headache. Text is in French.
- BH-029. Antique with wooden handle (Box 1, Folder BH.029)
  Rounded rectangle. 2nd of 8 fans with the same kind of black and white photograph in a light green architectural border. This fan's photograph is titled "A Morning Call" and noted as copyright 1902 by Chas. Williams. The product being promoted is "laxative celeri bromure" for headache. Text is in French.
- BH-030. Antique with wooden handle (Box 1, Folder BH.030)
  Rounded rectangle. 3rd of 8 fans with the same kind of black and white photograph in a light green architectural border. This fan's photograph is titled "This Little Pig Went to Market" and noted as copyright 1893 by W.H. Rau. The product being promoted is "laxative celeri bromure" for headache. Text is in French.
- BH-031. Antique with wooden handle (Box 1, Folder BH.031)
  Rounded rectangle. 4th of 8 fans with the same kind of black and white photograph in a light green architectural border. This fan's photograph is titled "And the cat came back" and noted as copyright 1894 by W.H. Rau. The product being promoted is "laxative celery bromide" for headache. Text is in English.
- BH-032. Antique with wooden handle (Box 1, Folder BH.032)
  Rounded rectangle. 5th of 8 fans with the same kind of black and white photograph in a light green architectural border. This fan's photograph is titled "And the cat came back" and noted as copyright 1894 by W.H. Rau. The product being promoted is "laxative celeri bromure" for headache. Text is in French.
- BH-033. Antique with wooden handle (Box 1, Folder BH.033)
  Rounded rectangle. 6th of 8 fans with the same kind of black and white photograph in a light green architectural border. This fan's photograph is titled "Nibbling at the bait" and noted as copyright 1897 by W.H. Rau. The product being promoted is "laxative celery bromide" for headache. Text is in English. Copy 1, identical to BH.034.
- BH-034. Antique with wooden handle (Box 1, Folder BH.034)
  Rounded rectangle. 7th of 8 fans with the same kind of black and white photograph in a light green architectural border. This fan's photograph is titled "Nibbling at the bait" and noted as copyright 1897 by W.H. Rau. The product being promoted is "laxative celery bromide" for headache. Text is in English. Copy 2, identical to BH.033.
- BH-035. Antique with wooden handle (Box 1, Folder BH.035)
  Rounded rectangle. 8th of 8 fans with the same kind of black and white photograph in a light green architectural border. This fan's photograph is titled "Nibbling at the bait" and noted as copyright 1897 by W.H. Rau. The product being promoted is "laxative celeri bromure" for headache. Text is in French.
- BH-036. Antique with wooden handle (Box 1, Folder BH.036)
  Badge-like shape. Color image of mountains with waterfall. W.A. Pierce, druggist, the Rexall store in West Chester, Pennsylvania.
- BH-037. Antique with wooden handle (Box 1, Folder BH.037)
  Badge-like shape. Color image of clown applying face paint to a boy. Fuhrer Brothers Pharmacy, the Rexall Store in Livingston Manor, New York.
- BH-038. Antique with wooden handle, 1935 (Box 1, Folder BH.038)
  Badge-like shape. Color portrait of an elegantly dressed woman. Fuhrer Brothers Pharmacy, the Rexall store in Livingston Manor, New York. Printer: Brown & Bigelow, St. Paul.
- BH-039. Antique with wooden handle (Box 1, Folder BH.039)
  Rounded rectangle. Painted winter night scene of country house with lighted windows. Selma Drug Company. Printer: Beckman Co., Philadelphia.
- BH-040. Antique with wooden handle (Box 1, Folder BH.040)
  Rounded rectangle. Painted scene of a river in a forest in the mountains. Selma Drug Company. Printer: Beckman Co., Philadelphia.
- Inventory and item notes provided by collector Bert Hansen, 2021 (Box 2)
- BH-041. Antique with wooden handle (Box 2, Folder BH.041)
  Rounded rectangle. Painted scene of a girl and her dog sitting in an elaborate garden outside her house. Selma Drug Company. Printer: Beckman Co., Philadelphia.
- BH-042. Antique with wooden handle (Box 2, Folder BH.042)
  Rounded square. Color painting of little girl on an old-fashioned wall phone, gold embossed thistle border. Wellman's Pharmacy, Tampa, Florida. Printer: Kemper-Thomas Company, Cincinnati, Ohio.
- BH-043. Antique with wooden handle (Box 2, Folder BH.043)
  Flattened circle. Painted illustration of two little boys in kilts and caps against a prominent yellow background. Publicity for brand 666 product line (liquid, tablets, salve, nose drops). L. E. Stauffer, druggist, Union Bridge. Printer: B. & B., St. Paul.
- BH-044. Antique with wooden handle (Box 2, Folder BH.044)
  Squarish badge shape. Front has painted illustration of little boy and 3 birds on a snowy branch, against a strong yellow background, singing the "666 Carol." Publicity for brand 666 product line (liquid, tablets, salve, nose drops). Bucher Pharmacy, Inc. Printer: U.O. Colson, Co., Paris, Illinois.
- BH-045. Antique with wooden handle (Box 2, Folder BH.045)
  Tall, narrow rectangle. Front has a black and white portrait photograph of "The dentist who does not hurt, Dr. Algase," likely of Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. Photographs of office, staff and price list for services.
- BH-046. Antique with wooden handle (Box 2, Folder BH.046)
  Large rounded badge shape. Walter Hufham, druggist, Morehead City, North Carolina. Publicity for various products carried by the Rexall agent. Printer: U.O. Colson Co., Paris, Illinois.
- BH-047. Antique with wooden handle (Box 2, Folder BH.047)
  Scalloped rectangle. Painted color illustration of four children around a table at birthday party, signed by Frances Tipton Hunter. H.C. Primm Co. (shoe store), Harper and Freeport.
- BH-048. Antique with wooden handle (Box 2, Folder BH.048)
  Rectangle. Publicity for Putnam Fadeless Dyes-Tints. Color image of Putnam founder E.N. Monroe with great granddaughter, Diann. P.E. Sander's Grocery, Shelbyville, Missouri. Printer: The Regensteiner Corporation, Chicago, Illinois.
- BH-049. Antique with wooden handle (Box 2, Folder BH.049)
  Rectangle. 2nd of 3 fans with publicity for Putnam Fadeless Dyes-Tints and other Putnam products. Drawing of woman painting the coloring on a large butterfly or moth's wings, with fairy helpers nearby holding pots of pigments. Sime & Barron, dry goods and groceries, Cottage Grove, Wisconsin.
- BH-050. Antique with wooden handle (Box 2, Folder BH.050)
  Rectangle. 3rd of 3 fans with publicity for Putnam Fadeless Dyes-Tints and other Putnam products. Drawing of woman painting the coloring on a large butterfly or moth's wings, with fairy helpers nearby holding pots of pigments. Hoornbeek Bros., Napanoch, New York. Printer: The Regensteiner Corporation, Chicago, Illinois.
- BH-051. Antique with wooden handle (Box 2, Folder BH.051)
  Flattened circle. Color illustration of "The Champion," a toddler as a boxer with gloved hands holding the rope. Healy Chapel, Aurora, Illinois. Printer: The Osborne Company, Clifton, New Jersey.
- BH-052. Vintage (Box 2, Folder BH.052)
  Circle. Publicity for Aunt Jemima products, with portrait drawing of the fictional African-American character and images from the concocted "Life of Aunt Jemima." R.T. Davis Milling Co., St. Joseph, Missouri.
- BH-053. Vintage (Box 2, Folder BH.053)
  Rounded rectangle. Image of Martin Luther King, Jr., with a framed picture of an unidentified woman, titled "Together Again." Winnfield Life Insurance Co., Natchitoches, Louisiana, with listings of branch offices and funeral homes in Louisiana. Copyright (printer?): A. Scheer.
- BH-054. Vintage (Box 2, Folder BH.054)
  Rounded rectangle. Portraits and quotations of John F. Kennedy, Martin Luther King, Jr., and Robert F. Kennedy, titled "These Americans Died For Freedom." House of Hills, Inc. Mortuary, Denver, Colorado. Photo of Thomas T. Hill, Licensed Mortician. Copyright (printer?): A. Scheer.
- BH-055. Vintage, 1968 (Box 2, Folder BH.055)
  Rounded rectangle. Color painting of "Mahalia Jackson, 1911-1972." Baker Funeral Homes, Inc. in Ft. Worth and Cleburne, Texas. Copyright (printer?): A. Scheer.
- BH-056. Vintage (Box 2, Folder BH.056)
  Rounded rectangle. Rural scene in color titled "Chapel in the Hills." Funk-Cooper-Warren Mortuary (and Ambulance Service), Lawrence, [Kansas]. Printer: Harley J. Scott, Kansas City, Missouri.
- BH-057. Vintage (Box 2, Folder BH.057)
  Rounded rectangle. Image of Black woman holding her baby up. Garland Bros. Funeral Home, Syracuse, New York.
- BH-058. Vintage (Box 2, Folder BH.058)
  Related Materials
  Rounded rectangle. Painting of Jesus with a flock of sheep, titled "The Good Shepherd." Feete Funeral Home, Brunswick, Maryland. Handwritten note on back: "June 1968, from United Church of Christ, Brunswick, MD 21716." Copyright (printer?): A. Scheer.
- BH-059. Vintage (Box 2, Folder BH.059)
  Bell-shaped cut out. Black College Fund, Division of Higher Education, General Board of Higher Education and Ministry, Nashville, Tennessee. With list of 12 historically black colleges and universities.
- BH-060. Vintage (Box 2, Folder BH.060)
  Rounded rectangle. Color image of farm boy with straw hat and a dog on his lap, titled "Hi There." Clarke-Wilson Funeral Service, but possibly a publisher/printer's marketing sample. Copyright (printer?): A. Scheer.
- BH-061. Vintage (Box 2, Folder BH.061)
  Rounded rectangle. Front image is a black and white photograph of a hearse. Morty the Mortuary Machine party car, central Pennsylvania. For funeral-themed prank parties, such as bachelor and bachlorette parties.
- BH-062. Vintage (Box 2, Folder BH.062)
  Rounded rectangle. Image titled "Christ in Gethsemane." George C. Carson and Sons Funeral Homes in Independence and Kansas City, Missouri. Copyright (printer?): A. Scheer.
- BH-063. Vintage (Box 2, Folder BH.063)
  Rounded rectangle. Color image of a white church with a high steeple titled "Chapel on the Hill." Center Place Savings, but limited other information so possibly a publisher/printer marketing sample. Copyright (printer?): A. Scheer.
- BH-064. Vintage (Box 2, Folder BH.064)